<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An impartial account of the state of New England, or, The late government there, vindicated in answer to the Declaration which the faction set forth when they overturned that government : with a relation of the horrible usage they treated the governour with , and his Council, and all that had His Majesty's commission : in a letter to the clergy there / by John Palmer.</title>
            <author>Palmer, John, 1650-1700?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1690</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 78 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A55052</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P246</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R37740</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">17008789</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 17008789</idno>
            <idno type="VID">105757</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A55052)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 105757)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1098:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An impartial account of the state of New England, or, The late government there, vindicated in answer to the Declaration which the faction set forth when they overturned that government : with a relation of the horrible usage they treated the governour with , and his Council, and all that had His Majesty's commission : in a letter to the clergy there / by John Palmer.</title>
                  <author>Palmer, John, 1650-1700?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>40 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Edward Poole ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1690.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dated (p. 40): From the Castle the twentieth day of June, 1689.</note>
                  <note>"Written by a member of the Council of Governor Andros, as a vindication of the deposed government, and in reply to 'The declaration of the gentlemen, merchants, and inhabitants of Boston, and the countrey adjacent.' It was first published anonymously, in 1689, at Boston or elsewhere in the colonies, under caption: 'The present state of New-England impartially considered, in a letter to the clergy.' The text of the London edition differs considerably from that of the American edition"--NUC pre-1956 imprints.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Declaration of the gentlemen, merchants, and inhabitants of Boston, and the countrey adjacent.</term>
               <term>Massachusetts --  History --  New Plymouth, 1620-1691.</term>
               <term>Massachusetts --  Politics and government --  1620-1691.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:105757:1"/>
            <p>AN IMPARTIAL ACCOUNT OF THE <hi>State of New England:</hi> OR, THE Late GOVERNMENT there, Vindicated.</p>
            <p>In Anſwer to the DECLARATION Which the FACTION ſet forth, when they Over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned That GOVERNMENT.</p>
            <p>With a Relation Of the Horrible Uſage they treated the Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour with, and his Council; and all that had His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty's Commiſſion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In a</hi> LETTER <hi>to the</hi> CLERGY <hi>there.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>John Palmer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Edward Poole,</hi> at the <hi>Ship</hi> over againſt the <hi>Royal Exchange,</hi> in <hi>Cornhill,</hi> 1690.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:105757:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:105757:2"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
            <p>THERE was ſo much Induſtry uſed in <hi>New England,</hi> by thoſe who had taken upon themſelves the Government, that nothing ſhould come abroad which might undeceive the People, already wrought to ſuch a pitch of Credulity, eaſily to believe the moſt monſtrous Lyes and Follies, that the enſuing Letter could not be Printed without exceſſive Charge and Trouble; the <hi>Preſs</hi> being forbid to any that were injur'd, to juſtifie themſelves, though open to all that would caluminate, and abuſe them; ſo that for ſeveral Months it appeared in Manuſcript, by ſtealth, branded with the hard Name of a Treaſonable and Seditious Libel; and would have been little better than Death, for any one, in whoſe Hands it ſhould have been found; but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained unanſwered, although Care was taken that it came to the Hands of ſome of the Perſons to whom it was directed.</p>
            <p>I was then oblig'd to conceal my Name, becauſe I was in their Hands, and liable to whatever their Malice could prompt them to impoſe upon me; but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing now at Liberty, and having reviſed it, I have thought fit, for the Juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Sir <hi>Edmond Andros,</hi> and the reſt of my Fellow-Sufferers, to make it publick here, that the World may ſee how barbarouſly we have been uſed, and moſt unmercifully dealt withal, by thoſe <hi>Profeſſing People;</hi> who for the better effecting the Subverſion of <hi>Kingly Government,</hi> and eſtabliſhing their Old <hi>Commonwealth,</hi> contrary to the Laws both of God and Man, and their <hi>Faith given;</hi> detain'd us Ten Months in Priſon, without any <hi>Mittimus,</hi> or juſt Cauſe, alledged for their ſo doing; and afterwards cauſed us to be put on Board, a deep loaden Ship, where we endured all the Miſeries of a Troubleſome Winter Voyage; but (by God's Bleſſing) eſcaped both the danger of the Seas, and our Enemies, and appeared at the Council-Board, where the worſt of our Enemies (even the <hi>very Men</hi> that had ſo unjuſtly impriſoned and detain'd us) had nothing to ſay or object againſt us.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:105757:3"/>Their Declaration (publiſhed as the Cauſe of their Inſurrection) is herein particalarly anſwered, and matter of Fact truly alledged, not in Scandalous, Baſe, and Abuſive Reflections, as ſome of their Pamphlets are ſtuff'd withal, but with that Sincerity and Moderation which becomes a Chriſtian; and altho' there are many things in it ſo frivolous, that to Men of Buſineſs, it may ſeem impertinent to anſwer; yet I hope to be excuſed, becauſe the meaneſt things made ſo deep an Impreſſion on the Vulgar and Ignorant People, that it was abſolutely neceſſary they ſhould be undeceived.</p>
            <p>I hope it will ſatisfie every unprejudiced Perſon, and ſufficiently convince the World that our Impriſonment was not for any Crime commmitted, but that (we being imployed from the Crown) by our Removal, the more eaſie Subver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of <hi>Monarchy,</hi> and Deſtruction of the <hi>Church of England,</hi> might be effected; both which they ever mortally hated, and had long before plotted to ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine, making uſe of this juncture of Affairs, and Their Majeſties Names to cloak their Deſign, whilſt their Service was never intended, as is evident by their withdrawing the Force from the Eaſt-ward, by which their Majeſties Fort and Garriſon of <hi>Pemyquid,</hi> and the whole County of <hi>Cornwall,</hi> the greateſt part of the Province of <hi>Mam,</hi> and part of the Province of <hi>New Hamp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire</hi> were loſt; the Inhabitants being driven from their Houſes, and above <hi>300</hi> of them taken Captives, and Murthered, by the <hi>Indians;</hi> embezling their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties Stores, Arms and Ammunition; ſeizing and diſmaniling their Fright, deſtroying their <hi>Revenue,</hi> ſetting up a <hi>Republick Government,</hi> making Laws, erecting Courts of Judicature, condemning and executing their Fellow Subjects, denying them Appeals to their Majeſties, and burthening them with intollerable Taxes, without any manner of Lawful Authority, for ſo doing, to the great Violation of the Laws, and deſtructive of the Liberty of the Subject.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:105757:3"/>
            <head>The State of <hi>NEW-ENGLAND,</hi> Impartially conſidered, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reverend Sirs,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>TWO Months have already paſt away, ſince, with Aſtoniſhment, I have beheld the moſt deplorable Condition of this Country; into what a <hi>Chaos</hi> of Confuſion and Diſtraction have this People run themſelves; and in what a labyrinth of Miſerys and Perplexitys are they involved! 'Tis high time now to make ſome ſerious Reflections on the State of Affairs.</p>
            <p>In the firſt place therefore, 'twill be neceſſary to conſider,</p>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>1.</hi> For what Reaſons, and to what End, did they take up Arms?</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>2.</hi> Whether thoſe Reaſons be Subſtantial, and ſuch as carry with them weight enough to juſtifie the Act; and whether the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed End can be obtained by ſuch Methods?</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>3. If not,</hi> What will be the Event, and whether any way be left open for a Peaceable and Friendly Settlement?</item>
            </list>
            <p>Although 'tis not a doubt but a prevailing Party among you, to gratifie their Malice, Ambition, or Revenge, have been the <hi>Plotters</hi> and <hi>Contrivers</hi> of theſe unhappy Troubles; and the better to carry it on, have made uſe of the deluded Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trymen,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:105757:4"/>as <hi>the Monkey did the Cats Foot, to pluck the Cheſnut out of the Fire:</hi> Yet I ſhall not meddle in that matter; I will on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly inſtance ſuch things as Converſation and Report have brought to my Knowledge, or as I ſhall find obvious in the <hi>Declaration;</hi> the ſum of which is:</p>
            <p n="1">1. That above ten Years ſince, there was an horrid Popiſh Plot in the Kingdom of <hi>England,</hi> in which the Extirpation of the <hi>Proteſtant Religion</hi> was deſign'd; and there was great rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to apprehend the Reform'd Churches of <hi>New-England</hi> were to be over-whelm'd in the ſame Pit of Ruine and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That the better to effect it, their <hi>Charter</hi> (the only Hedge which kept them from the wild Beaſts of the Field) was both injuriouſly and illegally Condemned, before it was poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for them to appear at <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> in the Legal Defence of it; and without a fair leave to anſwer for themſelves.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That by an illegal Commiſſion they were put under a Preſident and Council, which was ſoon ſuperceded by another, more Arbitrary and Abſolute, to Sir <hi>Edmond Andros,</hi> giving him Power, by the advice of his Council, to make Laws, and levy Taxes, as he pleaſed; to muſter and imploy all Perſons re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſident in the Territory, as occaſion ſhould require, and them to Transfer to any <hi>Engliſh</hi> Plantation; and that there were courſes taken to damp and ſpoil their Trade, while neither the Honour nor the Treaſure of the King was advanced.</p>
            <p n="4">4. That ſeveral Redcoats were brought over, to ſupport what ſhould be impoſed upon them, and more threatned.</p>
            <p n="5">5. That Preferments were principally loaden on Strangers and Haters of the People.</p>
            <p n="6">
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:105757:4"/>6. That they were Squeez'd and Oppreſs'd by a crew of abject Perſons from <hi>New York,</hi> who took, and extorted, extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary and intollerable Fees.</p>
            <p n="7">7. That it was impoſſible to know the Laws that were made, and yet dangerous to break them.</p>
            <p n="8">8. That by ſome in open Council, and by the ſame in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Converſe, it was affirmed, That the People in <hi>New Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> were all Slaves; and the only difference between them and Slaves, was their not being Bought and Sold; and that it was a Maxime delivered in open Court, by one of the Council, <hi>That they muſt not think the Privilege of</hi> Engliſh-men <hi>would follow them to the end of the World.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="9">9. That they were denied the Privileges of <hi>Magna Charta;</hi> and that Perſons who did but peaceably object againſt raiſing Taxes, without an Aſſembly, were for it ſeverely Fined.</p>
            <p n="10">10. That Juries have been pick'd and pack'd, and that ſome People have been Fined without a Verdict, <hi>yea, without a Jury.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="11">11. That ſome People have been kept long in Priſon, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any Information againſt them, or being charged with any Miſdemeanor, or <hi>Habeas Corpus</hi> allowed.</p>
            <p n="12">12. That Jury-men were Fined and Impriſoned for refuſing to lay their Hands upon the Book, as they came to be Sworn, contrary to the Common Law of <hi>New England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="13">13. That there was a diſcovery made of Flaws in the Titles of their Lands; and that the Governour denied that there was any ſuch thing as a Town among them, and that more than a few were by Terrors drawn to take Patents at exceſſive rates.</p>
            <p n="14">14. That <hi>Writs. of Intruſion</hi> were iſſued out.</p>
            <p n="15">15. That the Governour cauſed their Lands to be meaſured out for his Creatures, and that the right owners for pulling up
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:105757:5"/>the Stakes, have been grievouſly moleſted; and ſeveral Perſons had their Commons begg'd.</p>
            <p n="16">16. That the forcing of the People at the Eaſt-ward to take Patents, gave a riſe to the late unhappy Invaſion by the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dians.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="17">17. That blank Patents were got ready to be ſold at great Prices.</p>
            <p n="18">18. That the Governour, and five or ſix of the Council, did what they would; and that all ſuch as were Lovers of their Country, were ſeldom admitted.</p>
            <p n="19">19. That all manner of craft and rage was uſed to hinder Mr. <hi>Mather</hi>'s Voyage to <hi>England,</hi> and to ruine his Perſon.</p>
            <p n="20">20. That although the King promiſed Mr. <hi>Mather</hi> a <hi>Magna Charta</hi> for redreſs of Grievances; and that the Governour ſhould be Wrote unto, to forbear theſe meaſures that he was upon, yet they were ſtill injur'd in theſe very things which were complained of.</p>
            <p n="21">21. That the Miniſters and Churches have been diſcounte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanced.</p>
            <p n="22">22. That they were imbryar'd in an <hi>Indian</hi>-War; and that the Officers and Soldiers in the Army were under <hi>Popiſh Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manders.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="23">23. That the reſt of the Engliſh Plantations being alarm'd with juſt fears of the <hi>French,</hi> who have treated the <hi>Engliſh</hi> with more than <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Cruelty, could not but ſtir them up to take care for their own Preſervation, leſt they ſhould be delivered to the <hi>French,</hi> before Orders could come from <hi>His Hihgneſs the Prince of</hi> Orange, <hi>and the Parliament of</hi> England.</p>
            <p n="24">
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:105757:5"/>24. That they have for their Example, the Nobility, Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, and Commons of <hi>England;</hi> and above all, they eſteem it their Duty to God, ſo to have done.</p>
            <p>Thus far have I trac'd the <hi>Declaration,</hi> and do not know that any one thing material is omitted; I ſhall now mention ſome other Matters which have occurred.</p>
            <p>'Twas credibly Reported,</p>
            <p>That <hi>Boſton,</hi> and all the Inhabitants were to be deſtroyed; and to that end the <hi>Mohacques</hi> were to be brought down.</p>
            <p>That there were ſeveral Fire-works prepared in the Fort, and Vaults dug under Ground to blow up the Town.</p>
            <p>That the Soldiers at the Eaſt-ward were all poiſoned with Rum.</p>
            <p>That there were thirty Sail of <hi>French</hi> Frigats upon the Coaſt: With ſeveral other trifling things, which I cannot recollect.</p>
            <p>Theſe are the principal Reaſons alleaged for their taking up Arms; now the end can be no other than the redreſs of thoſe Evils' complained of.</p>
            <p>The next thing then to be conſidered of is, <hi>Whether all, or any of the Reaſons aforeſaid, are ſufficient to juſtifie their Procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings; and whether the propoſed end can be attain'd by ſuch Meaſures?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. That there was a Popiſh Plot is without doubt; and if <hi>England</hi> at that time had fallen under the Yoak of <hi>Roman Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny,</hi> 'tis as certainly true <hi>New England</hi> muſt have undergone the ſame Fate; but that this ſhould be uſed or introduced as a Reaſon or Argument for vacating their Charter, is beyond my Conception; for if they had once prevailed, How weak a ram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part would the Charter have been againſt ſo cruel and power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful an Enemy? Would the Papiſts have made <hi>Weſtminſter-Hall</hi> the Arbiter? Certainly no, their Will would have been their
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:105757:6"/>Law, and <hi>the Hedge would have been broke down,</hi> with a great deal of eaſe. Is it reaſonable to imagine, that after they had with Force and Violence attained their wiſhed-for End in Old <hi>England,</hi> they would make uſe of Politicks in New? And as prepoſterous and unreaſonable to Fancy, that for that end the Charter was called in Queſtion; eſpecially when you conſider, that four <hi>decades</hi> of Years have already paſt, ſince the Crown of <hi>England</hi> firſt thought it not fit for them to hold any long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er; and ſeveral Years after, the Popiſh Plot was diſcovered, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the <hi>Scire Facias</hi> iſſued out.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That the Charter was injuriouſly and illegally Condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, without giving them timely notice of it, or allowing them to anſwer for themſelves, might bear ſome weight with it, if true; but it will appear quite otherwiſe, and that they had opportunity enough to have made Defence on behalf of their Charter, if they had thought fit: For ſeveral Years before the proceedings to the Condemnation thereof, our late Soveraign King <hi>Churles</hi> the Second, by His Letters ſignified to them the many Complaints that were made to him of their Encroachments, and ill Adminiſtration of the Government; and to command that they ſhould ſend over Agents, ſufficiently Authorized, to anſwer the ſame; which at length they ſo far comply'd with, as to ſend them: But when they were called to hear, and anſwer the ſaid complaints, always excuſed and avoided the principal part thereof, pretending they were not ſufficiently impowered to that purpoſe; and afterwards other Agents were ſent, fully impowered to anſwer, but not to ſubmit or conclude any thing: And when His Majeſty was pleaſed to cauſe a Writ of <hi>Quo War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranto</hi> to be ſued forth againſt the <hi>Charter,</hi> and ſent over with his Gracious Declaration, and propoſals of ſuch Regulations
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:105757:6"/>to be made therein, as might be agreeable with His Majeſty's Service, and the good and welfare of his Subjects here, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired an intire ſubmiſſion thereto, the General Court would not ſubmit to, or comply therewith; only a Letter was ſent to the Right Honourable Sir <hi>Lionell Jenkins,</hi> then Secretary of State, Dated the <hi>10th.</hi> of <hi>December,</hi> 1683. Subſcribed by the Governour, and eight of the Aſſiſtants only, wherein, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the acknowledgment of their having had a Copy of the <hi>Quo Warranto,</hi> and his Majeſty's <hi>Declaration,</hi> they ſay, That the major part of the Magiſtrates have for ſeveral Weeks de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared their Opinion, and voted to lay themſelves at His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty's Feet, by an humble ſubmiſſion and reſignation of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to his Majeſty's pleaſure; not being willing to contend with his Majeſty in a courſe of Law, but by the next oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity to diſpatch their Agents fully impowered to make their Submiſſion according to his Majeſty's ſaid Declaration, but by no means can at preſent obtain the conſent of the <hi>Depuries,</hi> whereby to make it an Act of the <hi>Corporation;</hi> and therefore have agreed with them to a power of Attorneyſhip, to ſave a Default, in hopes that further time will prevail to diſpatch their Agents accordingly, and ſhall earneſtly endeavour to give the People a better underſtanding, before the next Ship Sail from hence.</p>
            <p>His Majeſty by this, finding that all the eaſie means he had uſed, could not bring them to any anſwer for the Crimes and Miſdemeanors laid to their charge, nor produce any thing elſe but baffles and delays, gave Order to his Attorney-General, to ſue out a Writ of <hi>Scire Facias</hi> from the High Court of <hi>Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cery,</hi> againſt the <hi>Governour and Company;</hi> which was accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly done, directed to the <hi>Sheriffs of London,</hi> &amp;c. and made
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:105757:7"/>returnable in <hi>Eaſter-Term,</hi> in the <hi>36th.</hi> Year of His Majeſty's Reign; wherein they were required to make known to the ſaid <hi>Governour and Company</hi> at <hi>London,</hi> That they appear in His Majeſty's High Court of <hi>Chancery</hi> at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> on the Day of the return thereof, to ſhew cauſe wherefore the ſaid <hi>Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> for the Reaſons in the ſaid Writ of <hi>Scire Facias</hi> mentioned and contained, ſhould not be made void, null, and cancell'd; and the Liberties and Privileges thereby granted to the ſaid <hi>Governour and Company,</hi> be Seized into the King's Hands; upon which Writ the ſaid <hi>Governour and Company</hi> not appearing, another Writ of <hi>Scire Facias,</hi> of the ſame Tenor iſſued forth, returnable in <hi>Trinity-Term,</hi> then next following, when the ſaid Governour and Company appeared by their conſtituted Attorney and Council; but refuſed to Plead to the ſaid Writ, only moved for time to ſend to <hi>New England,</hi> which not being agreeable with the Rules and Practice of the Court in ſuch Caſes, could not be allowed; but in Favour to them a Rule was made, That unleſs they Pleaded by the firſt day of the then next <hi>Michaelmas-Term,</hi> Judgment ſhould be entered by Default: And in that <hi>Term,</hi> for default of Pleading, Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was entered on His Majeſty's behalf, and the ſaid Charter adjudged to be void, null, and cancell'd, and that the Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and Privileges of the ſaid <hi>Governour and Company</hi> be Seiz'd into the <hi>King's Hands;</hi> which was accordingly done, by the <hi>Exemplification</hi> of the ſaid <hi>Judgment</hi> in the Reign of K. <hi>James</hi> the Second, and by His Majeſty's Commiſſion to a <hi>Preſident</hi> and <hi>Council</hi> to take the Government of this Countrey. All which Proceedings are moſt juſt and legal, according to the Rules and Practice of the Law of <hi>England,</hi> and agreeable with many Precedents of the like Nature, both ancient and modern.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:105757:7"/>Beſides, all Companies, Corporations, or Bodies Politick, made or granted by Letters Patents, or Charter, from His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, for any part or places beyond the Seas, are by them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves or Agents to be alwaies ready to anſwer His Majeſty in any of his Courts at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> when he ſhall think fit to or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der any Suit or Writ to be Sued or Proſecuted againſt them, and are ſuppoſed to be reſident in or about <hi>London</hi> or <hi>Weſtmin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter</hi> for that purpoſe, as the <hi>Eaſt-India, Royal African, Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moodos,</hi> and <hi>Hudſons-bay Companys are,</hi> who have their Trade, Factories, Collonys, and Plantations, abroad in <hi>Aſia, Africa,</hi> and <hi>America:</hi> And in the like ſtate or condition were <hi>the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany or Corporation of</hi> Maſſathuſets-Bay <hi>in</hi> New England to be, according to the Capacities given them by their Incorporation, of <hi>Suing and being Sued, Pleading and being Impleaded,</hi> as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears by the <hi>Dogget-Book of the Council,</hi> when the Charter was firſt Granted; wherein if they have neglected their Duty, as well as exceeded their Powers and Privileges granted, and would not put themſelves into a condition to be heard, when they ought and might, it is not His Majeſty, nor the proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of His Courts that are to be blamed, but themſelves.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That there was a Commiſſion ſent to the <hi>Preſident,</hi> and the ſucceſſive one, to Sir <hi>Edmond Andros,</hi> are both true; but that they were Illegal, is a Poſition too confidently aſſerted by the Pen-man, who ſeems to be more a <hi>Clergyman</hi> than a Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yer; but becauſe the well clearing up of this point will be of great ſervice to the ſubſequent Diſcourſe, 'twill not be amiſs that it be throughly conſidered. I ſhall therefore lay down this as a certain Maxime, both conſonant to Reaſon and the Laws of the Land, That <hi>thoſe Kingdoms, Principalities, and Collonies, which are of the Dominion of the Crown of</hi> England, <hi>and not of
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:105757:8"/>Empire of the King of</hi> England, <hi>are ſubject to ſuch Laws, Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances, and Forms of Government, as the Crown ſhall think fit to eſtabliſh.</hi> New England, <hi>and all the Plantations are ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to the Dominion of the Crown of</hi> England, <hi>and not to the Empire of the King of</hi> England: <hi>Therefore the Crown of</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land <hi>may Rule and Govern them in ſuch manner, as it ſhall think moſt fit.</hi> For the proof of which I ſhall inſtance <hi>Wales,</hi> which was once a Kingdom, or Territory, govern'd by its own Laws; but when it became of the Dominion of the <hi>Crown of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> either by Submiſſion or Conqueſt, it became ſubject alſo to ſuch Laws as King <hi>Edward</hi> the Firſt (to whom they ſubmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted) thought fit to impoſe, as may plainly appear in the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amble of the <hi>Statute of Rutland. Leges &amp; conſuetudines par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium illarum hactenus uſitatas, coram Nobis &amp; preceribus Regni noſtri fecimus recitari, quibus diligenter auditis, &amp; plenius in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tellectis quaſdam illarum de conſilio Procerum predictorum delevi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus quaſdam permiſſimus, &amp; quaſdam correximus, &amp; etiam quaſdam alias adjiciendas &amp; faciendas decrevinis, &amp; eas de caetero in terris noſtris in partibus illis perpetua firmitate teneri &amp; obſervari volumus, in forma ſubſcripta.</hi> We have cauſed the Laws and Cuſtoms of thoſe parts hitherto uſed, to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cited before Us, and the Peers of Our Realm, which being di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligently heard, and more fully underſtood, ſome of them, by the Advice of Our Peers aforeſaid, We have obliterated, ſome We have allowed, and ſome We have corrected; And have alſo Deereed, That ſome others ſhall be made; and We will, that for the future, they be holden and obſerved in Our Lands in thoſe parts, with perpetual Firmneſs in manner hereinafter expreſſed. Then follow the Ordinances, appointing Writs o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginal
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:105757:8"/>and judicial, in many things varying from thoſe of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and a particular manner of proceeding.</p>
            <p>And again, in the cloſe of the ſame Statute, <hi>Et ideo vobis Mandamus quod praemiſſa de caetero in omnibus obſervetis, ita tantum quod quotieſcunque quandocunque &amp; ubicunque Nobis pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuerit, poſſimus praedicta Statuta &amp; earum partes ſingulas decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rare, interpretari, addere ſive diminuere pro Noſtrae libito volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatis, pront ſecuritati Noſtrae &amp; Terrae Noſtrae viderimus expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri.</hi> And therefore We Command you. That from hencefor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward you obſerve the Premiſes in all things, ſo only, that as often, whenſoever, and whereſoever We pleaſe, We may Declare, Interpret, Add to, and Diminiſh from the ſaid Statutes, and every part of them, according to Our Will and Pleaſure, ſo as We ſhall ſee it expedient for the ſafety of Us, and Our Land aforeſaid.</p>
            <p>In the next place I ſhall inſtance <hi>Ireland:</hi> That it is a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer'd Kingdom is not doubted, [<hi>Cooke. Rep. Fol.</hi> 18.] but ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted in <hi>Calvin</hi>'s caſe, and by an Act of the <hi>11th. 12th.</hi> and <hi>13th.</hi> of King <hi>James,</hi> acknowledged in expreſs Words, <hi>viz. Whereas in former times the Conqueſt of this Realm, by His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty's moſt Royal Progenitors, Kings of</hi> England, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>That by virtue of the <hi>Conqueſt,</hi> it became of the Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the <hi>Crown</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> and ſubject to ſuch Laws as the Conqueror thought fit to impoſe, until afterwards by the Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters and Commands of <hi>H.</hi> 2. K. <hi>John,</hi> and <hi>H.</hi> 3. They were In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tituled to the Laws and Franchiſes of <hi>England,</hi> as by the ſaid Charters, reference being thereunto had, may more fully ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, I ſhall only inſtance two.</p>
            <p>The Firſt is out of the cloſe Rolls of <hi>H.</hi> 3. wherein the King, after Thanks given to <hi>G. de Mariſcis</hi> Juſtice of <hi>Ireland,</hi> ſignifies,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:105757:9"/>That himſelf, and all other his Lieges of <hi>Ireland,</hi> ſhould enjoy the Liberties which he had granted to his Lieges of <hi>England;</hi> and that he will grant and confirm the ſame unto them: [<hi>Clauſ.</hi> 1. <hi>H.</hi> 3. <hi>Dorſo</hi> 14.] which afterwards in the <hi>12th.</hi> Year of His Reign he did, as followeth; <hi>Rex dilecto &amp; fidelio ſuo</hi> Richardo de Burgo <hi>Juſticiar' ſuo</hi> Hibern. <hi>Salutem; Mandarimus vobis fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miter praecipientes, quatenus certo die &amp; loco faciatis venire co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram vobis, Archi-Epiſcopos, Epiſcopos, Abbates, Priores, Comi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes &amp; Barones Milites &amp; Libere Tenentes, &amp; Balivos ſingulo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum Comitatuum, &amp; coram eis publici legi faciatis Chartum Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini</hi> Johannis <hi>Regis Patris Noſtri, cui ſigillum ſuum appenſum eſt, quam fieri fecit, &amp; jurari a Magnatibus</hi> Hiberniae <hi>de legibus &amp; conſuetudinibus</hi> Angliae <hi>obſervandis in</hi> Hiberniae. <hi>Et praecipiatis eis ex parte noſtra, quod leges illas &amp; conſuetudines in Charta prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicta contentas de caetero firmiter teneant &amp; obſervent.</hi> The King to his Faithful and Beloved <hi>Richard de Burg</hi> Juſtice of <hi>Ireland</hi> Greeting. We have Commanded you, firmly enjoyning you, That on a certain day and place, you make to come before you the Arch-Biſhops, Biſhops, Abbats, Priors, Earls, Barons, Knights and Free-holders, and the Bayliffs of every County; and before them you cauſe to be publickly read the Charter of the Lord King <hi>John,</hi> our Father, to which his Seal is affixed, and which he cauſed to be made and Sworn to by the Nobility of <hi>Ireland,</hi> concerning the Laws and Cuſtoms of <hi>England</hi> to be obſerved in <hi>Ireland:</hi> And commanded them on our behalf, That for the future they firmly keep and obſerve thoſe Laws and Cuſtoms contained in the Charter aforeſaid.</p>
            <p>By all which it is evident, That after the Conqueſt, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the recited Charters, the Inhabitants there, although com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed of many <hi>Free-born Engliſh Subjects, who ſettled themſelves
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:105757:9"/>amongſt them,</hi> were neither govern'd by their own Laws, nor the Laws of <hi>England,</hi> but according to the good pleaſure of the Conqueror: And if you will take the Opinion of Sir <hi>Edward Coke,</hi> in his Annotations on the <hi>Great Charter,</hi> he tells you plainly, That at <hi>the making thereof, it did not extend to</hi> Ireland, <hi>or any of the King's Foreign Dominions;</hi> but after the making of <hi>Poyning's Law,</hi> which was in the <hi>11th.</hi> Year of <hi>H.</hi> 7, (long af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Great Charter) it did extend to <hi>Ireland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have only one Inſtance more, and that is, The uſage of Foreign Nations in their Plantations and Settlements abroad.</p>
            <p>The Governments of <hi>the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Provinces,</hi> and <hi>Denmark,</hi> are well known in <hi>Europe;</hi> and yet in all their Plantations, their Governments are deſpotical and abſolute, all the power is in the hands of a Governour and Council, and every thing is ordered and appointed by them, as is ſufficiently manifeſt to thoſe that are acquainted with <hi>Batavia, Surrinam, Curaſao, New York,</hi> (when formerly in their hands) <hi>and the Iſland of St.</hi> Thomas.</p>
            <p>By which it is evident, <hi>That thoſe Kingdoms and Principali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties which are of the Dominion of the Crown of</hi> England, <hi>are ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to ſuch Laws, Ordinances, and Methods of Government, as the Crown ſhall think fit to Eſtabliſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The next thing then to be proved is, <hi>That</hi> New England, <hi>and all the Engliſh Colonies, are ſubject to the Dominion of the Crown of</hi> England, <hi>as</hi> Wales <hi>and</hi> Ireland are, and not to the Empire of the King of <hi>England,</hi> as <hi>Scotland</hi> is.</p>
            <p>'Tis a fundamental point, conſented unto by all Chriſtian Nations, that the firſt Diſcovery of a Countrey inhabited by Infidels, gives a Right and Dominion of that Countrey to the Prince, in whoſe Service and Imployment the Diſcoverers was ſent: Thus the <hi>Spaniard</hi> claims the <hi>Weſt-Indies;</hi> the <hi>Portugals
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:105757:10"/>Braſile:</hi> and thus the <hi>Engliſh</hi> theſe Northern parts of <hi>America.</hi> For, <hi>Sebaſtian Cabot,</hi> imployed by King <hi>Henry</hi> 7. was the firſt Diſcoverer of theſe Parts, and in his Name took Poſſeſſion, which his Royal Succeſſors have held and continued ever ſince; therefore <hi>they are of the Dominion of the Crown of</hi> England; and as ſuch they are accounted by that excellent Lawyer Sir <hi>John Vaughan</hi> in his reports <hi>[Vauh. Rep. Craw verſus Ramſey.]</hi> which being granted, the Concluſion muſt neceſſarily be good, and it will follow; <hi>That Engliſhmen permitted to be Tranſported into the Plantations</hi> (for thither without the Kings Licence we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not come) <hi>can pretend to no other Liberties, Privileges, or Immuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties there, than anciently the Subjects of</hi> England, <hi>who removed themſelves into</hi> Ireland <hi>could have done:</hi> For it is from the Grace and Favour of the <hi>Crown</hi> alone that all theſe Flow, and are di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpenced at the pleaſure of him that ſits upon the Throne; which is plain in the great Charter it ſelf; where, after the Liberties therein granted by the King, it concluded thus—<hi>Tenendas &amp; habendas de Nobis &amp; haeredibus Noſtris in perpetuum.</hi> To have and to hold of Us, and Our Heirs for ever; which by the Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Sir <hi>Edward Coke</hi> is thus explained: <hi>Theſe words</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>are not inſerted to make a Legal Tenure of the King, but to intimate that all Liberties were at firſt derived from the Crown</hi> [<hi>Inſtit. page</hi> 2. <hi>fol.</hi> 4.] <hi>Barbados, Jamaica, the Leeward Iſlands,</hi> and <hi>Virginia</hi> have their Aſſemblies: but it is not <hi>ſui juris,</hi> 'tis from the grace and favour of the <hi>Crown,</hi> ſignified by <hi>Letters Patents under the Broad Seal.</hi> But the Laws made by theſe Aſſemblies with the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of the Governour, are no longer in force than till the King is pleaſed to ſignifie his Diſapprobation of them, which power he hath always reſer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o himſelf, and can, whenever he thinks fit, Repeal and Ann<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> all ſuch as have not been before confirmed by him, or ſome of his Predeceſſors.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:105757:10"/>
               <hi>New England</hi> had a <hi>Charter,</hi> but no one will be ſo ſtupid to imagine that the King was bound to grant it them, neither can you, without impeaching the prudent Conduct and Diſcretion of your Fore-Fathers, ſo much as think, they would put them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to ſo vaſt an Expence and unneceſſary Trouble to obtain that, which as <hi>Engliſh</hi> Men, they thought themſelves to have a ſufficient Right to before: They owe it only to the Grace and Favour of their Sovereign; and if they had made better uſe of it, to promote the Ends for which it was granted, the weight of thoſe Afflictions under which the People of this Country now groans, would not have lain ſo heavy upon them, at leaſt they would have leſs deſerved them.</p>
            <p>Beſides, the <hi>Parliament of England</hi> have never by any Act of theirs favoured the Plantations, or declared or inlarged their Privileges; but have all along demonſtrated, that they were much differenced from <hi>England,</hi> and not to have thoſe Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leges and Liberties which <hi>England</hi> enjoyed, being in all Acts re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating to the Plantations, reſtrained and burthened beyond any in <hi>England,</hi> as appears by the ſeveral Acts made for the increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of Navigation, and for regulating and ſecuring the Plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation Trade.</p>
            <p>I think I have both by good Authority, Practice and Prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent made it plain, That the Plantations are of the Dominion of the <hi>Crown of England,</hi> and without any regard to <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> may be rul'd and govern'd by ſuch ways and methods as the Perſon who wears that Crown, for the good and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement of thoſe Settlements, ſhall think moſt proper and convenient: therefore neither the Commiſſion to the <hi>Proſident,</hi> nor that to Sir <hi>Edmond Andros,</hi> can be ſaid to be Illegal.</p>
            <p>Since then ſuch an one might lawfully be granted, you have
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:105757:11"/>great reaſon to commend the Moderation of the Gentleman who was intruſted with it, and to return Thanks to Almighty God, for placing over you a Perſon indued with that Prudence and Integrity, that he was ſo far from exceeding his Commiſſion, that he never put in execution the powers therein granted him. Have there been any Taxes laid upon the People, but ſuch as were ſettled fifty years ſince, and made perpetual by Laws of their own making? Any part whereof might be retained, and in force, after the condemnation of their Charter, that the King thought fit Who hath been transferr'd out of this Territory? Or were ever fewer Rates paid than under him?</p>
            <p>And whereas it is alſo alleaged in the Declaration, That there were courſes taken to <hi>damp</hi> and <hi>ſpoil</hi> their <hi>Trade,</hi> while neither the Honour nor Treaſure of the King were advanced: Give me leave to tell you, the ſame is altogether falſe, and miſtaken, for the very conſiderable increaſe of Their Majeſties <hi>Revenue</hi> ariſing by Cuſtoms (not at all altered under Sir <hi>Edmond</hi>'s government) doth ſufficiently demonſtrate that the regular and lawful Trade of this Territory was exceedingly improved under him: 'Tis true, the Acts for Regulating the Plantation-Trade, and Naviga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion (little regarded under the Maſſathuſets Government, to the great prejudice of the Revenues of the Crown, and detriment of its European Subjects) were carefully inforced, and their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant and profitable correſpondence with Foreigners and Pyrats diligently obſtructed, (which was very diſagreeable to many Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons who had even grown old in that way of Trade, and was I believe one chief cauſe of the Revolution, which ſeems evident by their falling again upon the ſame meaſures ſince that change.) By this is meant <hi>Courſes taken to damp and ſpoil their Trade,</hi> for which I hope the Government will not lie under any imputations in the Judgment of conſidering Men.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:105757:11"/>I ſhall ſay little concerning the King's Treaſure; for it is clear to all that know this Country, that under the late Government, there was never ſo few Taxes paid, nor until the <hi>Indian Rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> a fuller Treaſury ſince the ſettlement of theſe parts; and 'tis plain, That the alteration of the Maſſethuſets Government, and annexation of the reſt of thoſe petty Colonys did highly conduce to the King's Honour, and the good and welfare of his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects; for all that Country which was every day ſubject to the Incurſions of the <hi>French,</hi> was no ſooner taken into the King's hands, and united, but they became formidable: And all en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours to make them demoliſh the Fort of <hi>Oneagra,</hi> (which they had Built and Garriſoned ſome hundreds of Miles within the <hi>Engliſh Dominions,</hi> in the Year 1687) proved unſucceſsful, until the Union of the ſaid Colonys, under the Commiſſion ſo much complained of: And I do heartily wiſh, that the Diviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons now among you, do not encourage them to take the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage of this opportunity, and by an utter deſtruction of all this <hi>Continent,</hi> experimentally make good my Aſſertion.</p>
            <p>And 'tis as plain that the King's Subjects, which for many years had groaned under the ſeverlty of a Tyrannical and Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitrary Conſtitution, deprived of the Laws and Liberties of <hi>Engliſh-men,</hi> forced in their Conſciences, ſuffered death for Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and denied <hi>Appeals</hi> to the King, were eaſed of thoſe intolera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Burthens, and allowed the free Exerciſe of their Religion, and the benefit of the Laws of <hi>England,</hi> which were duly and truly adminiſtred unto them, by which the Honour of the King is advanced to the higheſt pitch.</p>
            <p n="4">4. 'Twill be but time loſt to ſay any thing of the Red-coats; for no body can be ſo void of Senſe and Reaſon to think that ſo many Thouſand Men, which at this day inhabit this Colony,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:105757:12"/>could be impoſed upon by 100 Red-coats; and if any body hath been ſo vain as to threaten them with more, I look upon it an effect of paſſion or folly; For Experience, which certainly is the moſt convincing Argument in the World, tells you there is no ſuch thing.</p>
            <p n="5">5. What is meant by Preſerments, and who are called Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers and Haters of the People, I muſt confeſs I cannot eaſily comprehend, unleſs to inhabit fourteen or fifteen Years within the Territory will make a Man ſuch. Is there any one Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of the Council, that hath either been diſplaced, or put in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to that Station by the Authority there? Which of your Judges are Strangers? Were not Three of them brought up amongſt you; and of your own Communion? And was not the other in the ſame Imployment in ſome part of this Territory, at the time of the Annexation? From whom had the Secretary and Collector his Commiſſion? Certainly from no body here. Did the alteration of the Government change your Treaſurer? Is it not the ſame Sir <hi>Edmond</hi> found here? Is he not a Man of Eſtate, good Credit and Reputation, and one of your own Countrymen? Were not all Officers in the Government, as well Magiſterial as Miniſterial, natural born <hi>Engliſhmen,</hi> and Subjects to the Crown of <hi>England?</hi> How then are Strangers and Haters of the People preferr'd, when there is not one that can reaſonably and juſtly be ſo termed, in any place of Truſt or Office throughout the Dominion.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Who are meant by abject Perſons from <hi>New York</hi> wants an Explanation, for none of the Gentlemen that came from thence, (now in any Authority) but are well known to have liv'd there for a long time, in Eſteem and Reputation, enough to merit a better <hi>Epethite</hi> of all good and honeſt Men; and I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:105757:12"/>it will one day appear, that their Faithful diſcharge of their Duties, their conſtancy and ſteadineſs to <hi>the Church and Laws of England,</hi> and unſhaken Loyalty and Fidelity to the Crown, was their greateſt Crime.</p>
            <p>I am not well acquainted what Fees were taken, but this I know, that a Committee of the Council were appointed to make a ſettlement of Fees for all Officers throughout the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, which was effected, approved of, and ſent to <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land;</hi> and if any one have exceeded thoſe Limits, they deſerve to be called to account, but it ought to be in a due courſe of Law. For the perſonal miſcarriages of a Miniſterial Officer, are no ſufficient Warrant for an Inſurrection; neither ought the whole Government to be Subverted, becauſe <hi>Tom</hi> or <hi>Harry</hi> are ill Men. The Authority can but provide good and wholſome Laws for the puniſhment of Evil doers, and cauſe thoſe Laws to be put in execution againſt Offenders: But if any one doth me a perſonal wrong, for which I have a Remedy by Law, and I will not take it, I ought not to quarrel with the Government, for 'tis my own Fault, and I might have redreſs if I would. Perſonal Crimes muſt be cenſured Perſonally; and a Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ought no more to be ſcandalized and aſperſed, becauſe an Extortioner is in it, than becauſe there is a <hi>Felon</hi> or a <hi>Traitor.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7. I need not tell you that the Statute Laws of <hi>England</hi> are Printed at large, and that many Abridgments of them are ſo likewiſe, and eaſie enough to be procured; neither can it be but very well known, that all the Acts of the Governour and Council were ſolemnly publiſhed with Sound of Trumpet, as ſoon as made, and Authentick Copies afterwards tranſmitted to the Clerks of each reſpective County throughout the Terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory; Why then it ſhould be ſaid, that it was impoſſible to know
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:105757:13"/>the Laws? I ſee no reaſon, unleſs by it is meant <hi>the Common Law;</hi> and if ſo, you may as well quarrel becauſe every com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Perſon doth not underſtand <hi>Euclid</hi> or <hi>Ariſtotle;</hi> for the knowledge of the Law, cannot be attained without great In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtry, Study, and Experience; and every Capacity is not fitted for ſuch an Undertaking, <hi>Ex quovis Ligno non fit</hi> Mercurius. If this was a Grievance, What a miſerable condition are they in now, that inſtead of not knowing the Law, there is no Law for them to know?</p>
            <p n="8">8. What raſh, or indiſcreet, Expreſſions may fall from any ſingle Perſon of the Council, either in his private or politick Capacity, I will not undertake to juſtifie; all Men are not endued with qualifications alike; every one in that Station ought to give his Opinion, as he himſelf underſtands the Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; and if any one have unadviſedly uttered Words ſo diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agreeable, I know no Body injur'd by it, neither can the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment be juſtly cenſur'd for it.</p>
            <p n="9">9. That the Privileges of <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> and other Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of <hi>Engliſh-men</hi> were denied them, is a thing which can never be made appear; however, admitting it, I have ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently diſcuſs'd that Point in the Third Article. By the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons ſaid to be ſeverely Fined, for peaceably objecting againſt raiſing of Taxes without an Aſſembly, I conjecture are meant the <hi>Ipſwich-men,</hi> who were ſo far from a peaceable objecting, that they aſſembled themſelves in a <hi>riotous manner,</hi> and by an Inſtrument conceived in Writing, did <hi>Aſſociate</hi> and oblige themſelves to ſtand by each other in oppoſition to the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and by their Example, influenced their Neighbours to do the like. And this by the Law is eſteemed an Offence of that Nature, that it is next door to <hi>Rebellion;</hi> for which they were
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:105757:13"/>Indicted, Tryed, and Convicted, either by <hi>Verdict</hi> or their own <hi>Confeſſion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="10">10. I cannot juſtifie that Sheriffs, who doth either pick or pack a Jury; 'tis both repugnant tothe Law and his Oath; and he deſerves no favour, that can be Guilty of ſuch a Crime; but let him firſt be known, and the thing proved; for I do not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member any one that hath been Convicted, nor ſo much as ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed for ſuch an Offence.</p>
            <p>Judgments upon <hi>Demurers</hi> and Defaults, are ſo practicable and warrantable, by the Law, that nothing can excuſe the enu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merating them amongſt the Grievances in the <hi>Declaration,</hi> but the Pen-man's want of Knowledge in that Profeſſion. 'Tis a Maxime, <hi>Volenti non fit injuria;</hi> and when both Plantiff and Defendant do, by a joynt conſent, ſubmit to the determination of the Court, or by their own negligence make default; Who hath the wrong? Where is the Injury? This hath been a pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctico ſo frequently uſed in your <hi>former Government</hi> (though under another Name) that no body can be ignorant of it.</p>
            <p n="11">11. That any one hath been Impriſoned, without being charged with Crime or Miſdemeanour, is an Allegation which I dare be bold to ſay can never be proved; I have heard indeed an <hi>Habeas Corpus</hi> demanded upon the Statute of the 31. <hi>C.</hi> 2. was denied in Major <hi>Appleton</hi>'s Caſe, (who was one of the <hi>Ip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwich</hi>-men before-mentioned;) but let any conſidering Man peruſe the Act, and I believe he will be eaſily convinced, that it is particularly limitted to the Kingdom of <hi>England;</hi> beſides, he was committed only becauſe he would not find Sureties for the good Behaviour, and the queſtion was not whether he ſhould be Bailed; for upon finding the ſaid Sureties, he muſt have been diſcharged of courſe; ſo that it was not the want of
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:105757:14"/>an <hi>Habeas Corpus</hi> detain'd him in Priſon, but his own wilful and obſtinate Humour; if they do but conſider well how many Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen lie now in ſtinking Goals, and cloſe Priſons, without ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Mittimus</hi> or <hi>Crime</hi> laid to their charge, and without the allowance of an <hi>Habeas Corpus,</hi> although demanded; I am ſure they cannot but bluſh, when they read that part of the Declaration.</p>
            <p n="12">12. That Jurymen were fined and impriſoned for refuſing to lay their hands to the Book, I preſume is a miſtake; probably they may have been fined for their contempt, and ſent to Priſon for not paying that Fine, which by the Law may be Juſtified; for evrey Court may fine any man for a contempt in open Court, and they themſelves are Judges of the Contempt.</p>
            <p>Whether it be a forcing of Conſcience or not, I ſhall leave to Caſuiſts; but I am very well ſatisfied, <hi>it is not comprehended with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the late Indulgence:</hi> Yet admit it were, the Judges are ſworn to do their Duties in their Offices, according to the Laws of the Land: <hi>Preſcription is a good and ſufficient Law,</hi> the form of lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Hand upon the Book hath been the only <hi>modus</hi> of Swear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing time out of mind; therefore the laying the Hand on the Book in Swearing, is a good Law, and the Judges cannot diſpence with it, <hi>Salvo Sacramento;</hi> if they did, a Judgment in ſuch a caſe would be erroneous and reverſible, and <hi>'tis dangerous to admit of Innovations.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Common Law of <hi>New England</hi> is brought in, to Warrant the lifting up the Hand; but I take that to be <hi>rara Avis in Terris;</hi> for I challenge the whole Territory to produce one <hi>Precedent</hi> of ſuch a <hi>reſolved</hi> caſe; but perhaps by it, Preſcription is intended; if it be, that will as illy ſerve the turn as th'other; for the Colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny hath not been long enough ſettled, to claim any advantage by that Right; neither if it had, would it be admitted without appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:105757:14"/>violation of their <hi>Charter,</hi> being abſolutly repugnant to the Laws of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="13">13. Fully to diſcuſs the queſtion concerning the Titles of their Lands, would be a Subject too Copious for the preſent Deſign, therefore I ſhall only glance at it as I paſs by, being reſolved, when time ſhall ſerve, to declare my Opinion more amply on that Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject; in the mean time, let every conſidering Man Examine well the <hi>Charter,</hi> which is the very <hi>baſis</hi> of all their Rights, (unleſs they will ſet up a Power above the Kimgs,) and then let him tell me, in whom the <hi>Fee ſimple</hi> of that Tract of Land, betwixt <hi>Charles</hi>'s <hi>River</hi> and <hi>Merry-mack</hi> remains: if in the <hi>Grantees or their Heirs,</hi> How do they derive their Titles form them? If in the <hi>Governour and Company of the Maſſathuſets Bay,</hi> they muſt inquire whether pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuant to the Directions and Powers to them granted, it is by good and ſufficient Conveyances in the Law, derived unto them. If they find it ſo, they muſt not be diſturbed with Fears and Jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſies, for nothing can hurt them, if not, they are infinitely obliged to thoſe Perſons who have made them ſenſible of their Weakneſſes, in a time, when by His Majeſties <hi>Letter Patents,</hi> the <hi>Governour</hi> was impowered to ſupply all ſuch Defects, and not upon Terms, either exceſſive or unreaſonable, but upon ſuch as were both eaſy and moderate, which will plainly appear to any Man who will but give himſelf the trouble to peruſe the Table of Fees, ſettled and allowed by the Council; yet ſtill every Man was at his own Liberty, to take a <hi>Patent of Confirmation,</hi> or to let it alone, as is apparent enough by the many Petitions now lying in the Secretary's Office, which, altho' his Excellency was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways ready (ſo far as in him lay) to Grant, yet the more neceſſitous Affairs of the Govermment, which both he, and all about him, ever preferr'd to their private advantage, took up ſo much of
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:105757:15"/>his time, that not above twenty ever paſſed the Seal; and I am very well aſſured, that not one Example can be produced, that the leaſt compulſion was ever uſed in this caſe, to any Man liv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, within this Dominion.</p>
            <p>If the Governour did ſay, there was no ſuch thing amongſt you as a Town, what can be inferred from thence? 'Tis not to be preſum'd, but his Diſcourſe tended only to a Body Corporate and Publick: For you generally call that a Town in <hi>America,</hi> where a number of People have Seated themſelves together, yet 'tis very well known, 'tis ſo in <hi>Name</hi> only, not in Fact: I take that Body of People to be a Town, properly ſo called, who by ſome Act of Law, have been <hi>Incorporated,</hi> and in that ſenſe there is no ſuch thing as a Town in the <hi>Maſſathuſets,</hi> neither was there a Power to make ſuch before his Excellency's Arrival, for <hi>One Corporation cannot make another.</hi> [The Caſe of <hi>Suttons Hoſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal. Co. Rep.</hi>]</p>
            <p n="14">14. That <hi>Writs of Intruſion</hi> were iſſued out, is doubtleſs true, and the Government would have juſtly merited a ſevere cenſure, if all waies ſhould have been free and open, for the Subject to attain his right, and none left for the King. They would think themſelves highly injur'd to be refuſed a <hi>Capias</hi> or any other common Writ; and I'm ſure the other is as peremptory an one in the Kings Caſe; and had the Penman been never ſo little ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with the <hi>Natura brevium,</hi> or the <hi>Regiſter,</hi> he would have been aſham'd to have ſtuffed up the Declaration with ſuch Matter, which can be of no other ſervice, than to amuſe and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive ignorant People. Have there been more than ſeven Writs of this kind iſſued out, during Sir <hi>Edmonds</hi> Adminiſtration? Or more than two Proſecuted? And were any of them againſt either <hi>Poor</hi> or Ignorant Perſons, that had neither Purſes nor Brains to
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:105757:15"/>defend themſelves. Hath it not been againſt ſuch, as both for their Eſtates and Capacities, are ſufficiently known to be emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent? And the buſineſs of <hi>Deer-Iſland</hi> was brought on for no other intent, then that right might be done to the King here, and that the Party, if agrieved, might in a regular way have brought it to the Council-Board in <hi>England</hi> for their Determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation: And I think, if this matter were rightly underſtood, it would be of excellent ſervice to the Country, for ſuch a Judgment would ſufficiently inſtruct them what they have to truſt to.</p>
            <p n="15">15. That their Commons might be begg'd, is not very ſtrange; but that the Governour muſt be Criminal becauſe ſuch a thing is asked of him, is a barbarous inference: To whom have they been granted? Or for which of his <hi>Creatures</hi> have they been <hi>meaſured out?</hi> I ſhould be glad to ſee that Man who would bare-fac'd inſtance one partioular grant of any Man's Right or Poſſeſſion paſſed by Sir <hi>Edmond,</hi> during his Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. 'Tis true, that at the requeſt of Lieutenant Coll. <hi>Lidget,</hi> (a Gentleman who hath long lived among you in Reputation, equal to the beſt, whoſe Fortunes were not ſo narrow, that he needed a dependance upon any one, and by a plentiful Eſtate, which he poſſeſſed in <hi>Charles-Town,</hi> had a right to a propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionable ſhare or dividend in all the vacant and unapropriated Lands belonging to the ſaid Town,) the Governour and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil did grant him a piece of the ſaid vacant Lands, (which the Pen-man corruptly calls Commons) contiguous to a very conſiderable Farm, which he was there owner of, which I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume they might very lawfully do; for it can never be made appear, That the People of <hi>Charles-Town,</hi> either in Law or Equity, had a Right or Title to the ſaid Land, without a
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:105757:16"/>Grant from the Governour and Company of the <hi>Maſſathuſet</hi>'s Bay, exempted under the Seal of the Corporation, purſuant to the Rules and Directions of their Charter, they can have no Legal Claime; and I am fure, ſuch can never be produced, and I think they have as ſlender a pretence to an equitable one, when the Land hath always lain waſt and undivided, to the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit and advantage of the Claimer, without any manner of charge or expence.</p>
            <p>Beſides, it cannot be conſiſtent with the Intereſt of new Plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, that two or three Hund. Thouſand Acres of Land ſhould be taken up by a ſmall number of People, who are not capable of improving one tenth part of it, and the reſt lie vacant under the notion of Commons, when Perſons of Ability, equally concerned, would improve it, but cannot, becauſe they are leſs numerous than the poorer ſort of the Town, whoſe ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage it is that the Lands ſhould ſo lie, and who manage their Affairs by majority of Voices. And if the Tract of Land which <hi>Charleſtowne</hi> pretends to, were proportionally divided, Coll. <hi>Lidgett's</hi> ſhare (they themſelves being Judges) would have exceeded the Grant.</p>
            <p>'Tis likewiſe true, that <hi>Clark</hi>'s <hi>Iſland</hi> was granted to Mr. <hi>Clark</hi> of <hi>Plymouth,</hi> which might very well be, for it was never in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded within the <hi>Plymouth</hi> Patent, and ſo reſolved by the Council in that caſe, and therefore grantable at the King's Pleaſure. And this is all that I know of which can be objected.</p>
            <p>It may be true, that ſome Perſons who have contemptuouſly and riotouſly obſtructed the Surveyor-General, in the doing of his Office, and pluck'd up, and removed the Stakes and Land<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marks ſet up by him, upon vacant and unappropriated Lands, have been upon Legal Tryal and Conviction moderately Fined
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:105757:16"/>for their Offence, but ſee no reaſon that ſhould be accounted a Crime in any, or that ſuch Actions ſhould eſcape unpuniſhed.</p>
            <p n="16">16. I am likewiſe in the dark, to find out how the forcing of the People at the Eaſt-ward to take Patents (although I know of no ſuch thing done) gave a riſe to the late unhappy Invaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on by the <hi>Indians,</hi> unleſs by that means the <hi>Indians</hi> were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prived of thoſe quit-rents and acknowledgments, which by a baſe and diſhonourable agreement, made by Commiſſioners ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed from <hi>Boſton,</hi> the People of thoſe parts, ſome time ſince, were obliged to pay them, as their <hi>Lords and Maſters.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="17">17. I am totally ignorant what is meant by <hi>Blank Patents,</hi> for 'tis the firſt time <hi>I</hi> ever heard of ſuch a thing, neither indeed can it be; for he that takes a Patent for his Land, doth it in ſuch a form as beſt pleaſeth himſelf, or as he ſhall be adviſed to by his Council; And how any Man living can ſo far know my mind to prepare ſuch an <hi>Inſtrument</hi> for me, <hi>I</hi> leave the World to judge.</p>
            <p n="18">18. That any of the Council were ever denied admittance to that Board, is a thing ſo apparently falſe, that I'm ſure not a Man amongſt them but muſt juſtifie the Governour in that point; who was always ſo far from ſuch a Method, that although there was a certain day appointed for their meeting every Week, <hi>well known to them all;</hi> yet it was a frequent thing for him to ſend on purpoſe to <hi>Salem,</hi> and other Neighbouring Parts, for the Gentlemen that lived there; and I have ſeen the Meſſengers Account, wherein he chargeth a conſiderable Summ of Mony for Horſe-hire on thoſe Errands. 'Tis very well known, his Excellency hath waited many Hours for ſeveral of the Gentlemen that live in Town, and would never Sit until they came; and as he hath never done, nor ordered the leaſt matter relating to
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:105757:17"/>the Government, without their <hi>advice and conſent;</hi> ſo he ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver did it without a ſufficient number to make a <hi>Quorum,</hi> which was Seven.</p>
            <p n="19">19. There was never any other Courſe taken, to hinder Mr. <hi>Mather</hi>'s Voyage to <hi>England,</hi> than what the Law allows; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can the Government, without a great deal of Injuſtice, be charged with any thing relating to that Matter, for <hi>none in place knew his Errand.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There was a particular difference between Mr. <hi>Randolph</hi> and him; and <hi>I</hi> never heard of any other Courſe, taken by Mr. <hi>Ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolph,</hi> than the ordinary Writ in ſuch Caſes uſual; which was ſo far from retarding his Voyage, that <hi>an Attorney's entring a common Appearance,</hi> in that Caſe, would have been ſufficient to have diſcharged him, if the Writ had been ſerved.</p>
            <p n="20">20. Suppoſe the King promiſed Mr. <hi>Mather,</hi> a certain <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> for Redreſs of <hi>(imaginary)</hi> Grievances; and that his Excellency ſhould be wrote unto to forbear the Meaſures he was upon; yet no ſuch thing being done, he was obliged to the Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervance of His Majeſty's Commands, before ſignified to him in his <hi>Letters Patents;</hi> which was a ſufficient Warrant to him, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til he ſhould receive ſome thing ſubſequent to contradict it.</p>
            <p n="21">21. That your Churches and Miniſters have been diſcoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, is ſo general an Head, and the reſt of the Declaration ſo particular, that it gives me cauſe to ſuſpect the truth of it; and <hi>I</hi> ſhall hardly alter my Opinion, until any one of you be inſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, who kept himſelf within his Province, and only medled with that which belong'd to him.</p>
            <p>'Tis the <hi>Church of England</hi> that hath moſt reaſon to complain, only you <hi>cry Whore firſt:</hi> For at Sir <hi>Edmond</hi>'s Arrival, they were the only People deſtitute of a Place to Worſhip in, until,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:105757:17"/>by Advice and Conſent of the Council, the New Meeting Houſe, in <hi>Boſton,</hi> was borrowed, and made uſe of by them, but at inconvenient Hours; in the Morning after Eleven, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times as their Service was prolong'd at Twelve; and after Four in the Afternoon, which with patience was endured, tho' the Enmity of that People, to the Church of <hi>England,</hi> was ſuch, that they grudged them that ſmall Accomodation, and ſhewed their uneaſineſs therein; which was ſoon removed, by the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour's encouraging a Church to be built, and compleated in <hi>Boſton,</hi> at the Charge of thoſe of that Communion, where the Publick Worſhip, and Service of God hath been attended, until the late Inſurrection, when the Miniſter was forced to leave the Countrey, and Church, for his own ſafety; And has not the Miniſter been before this publickly affronted, and hindred from doing of his Duty? What ſcandalous Pamphlets have been Printed to villifie the Liturgy? And are not all of that Communion daily called <hi>Papiſt Doggs, and Rogues,</hi> to their Faces? How often has the plucking down the Church been threatned? One while, it was to be converted to a School, and anon, 'twas to be given to the <hi>French Proteſtants.</hi> And whoſo will but take the Pains to ſurvey the Glaſs Windows, will eaſily diſcover the Marks of a Malice not common; I believe 'tis the firſt National Church, that ever lay under ſuch great Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>advantages, in a Place, where thoſe that diſſent from her, ought to expect all things from her Grace and Favour.</p>
            <p n="22">22. Should I undertake to recount all the particulars of the late <hi>Indian Rebellion,</hi> this would ſwell to a bulk bigger than ever I deſigned it; I ſhall only tell you, you muſt look at home; for the reaſons of thoſe troubles, which is well known, began when his Excellency was above Five Hundred Miles off at <hi>New
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:105757:18"/>York,</hi> and that the Folly and Raſhneſs of the People, drew it on their own Heads. The Governours Conduct in that Affair has been ſo prudent and diſcreet, that I have no reaſon to doubt but your Council of Safety, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Into whoſe hands, all the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers relating to that buſineſs did fall, are very well ſatisfied with it: Was not the whole Country ſo ſecured, that not the leaſt Damage, or Spoil was done to the Plantations and Fiſhery, du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the Forces being abroad? And were not the <hi>Indian</hi> Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies by the ſaid Forces, hard Marches, and Purſuits, ſomtimes above One Hundred Miles into the Deſart, beyond any Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Settlement, reduced to the extreameſt Wants and Neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities? And all things brought to that paſs, that if our unhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py Domeſtick Troubles had not intervened, the War before this time would have been advantageouſly Finiſhed, without any Rates or Taxes, on the Country; for by his Excellencies good Husbandry, the ſtanding Revenue would have defrayed the Charge: 'Tis true, you have loſt ſome of your Friends and Relations in that Expedition; but could the <hi>Governour</hi> keep them a Live? Are not Diſeaſes in Armies as Fatal to Men as the Sword? When Death comes, 'tis not to be avoided; and you ſee that all your Art and Care hath not been ſufficient to Preſerve your deareſt Friends at Home, from the greater Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cality which hath run through this Crountry; Did any of them Dye neglected? Which of them wanted any thing to be had in thoſe Parts? Did his Excellency lye upon Beds of Down, and fare Deliciouſly every Day? No, the ſame Meat, the ſame Drink, the ſame Lodging in their Quarters, and Marches very common to all; only he was generally the leaſt taken care for: To what a degree of Madneſs and Impiety are we then grown, ſo <hi>Falſly and Maliciouſly,</hi> to Re-criminate a Perſon, who for
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:105757:18"/>your Defence and Security, hath ſo generouſly expoſed himſelf to the <hi>Hardſhips</hi> of that Cold and Uncomfortable Clymate, and the Fatigues of War, againſt a Barbarous and Savage People? And certainly if God Almighty hath not <hi>given over this People to believe Lies,</hi> their Eyes muſt be by this time open, and they cannot but know, how much they have been put upon, Shamm'd and Abus'd. Who are <hi>Popiſh Commanders</hi> in the Army? Will any Man Bare-fac'd Aver ſo great an untruth? It muſt be Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed, there was one and no more, under that Circumſtance, who had the Command of a Company of the King's ſtanding Forces, and was not Commiſſioned for the Army; beſides, if he had, hath he not Lived long amongſt us? Did any one ever queſtion his Ability, Courage, Fidelity and Conduct, and ought not that Liberty of Conſcience, which has been ſo hotly Preached up, even to the Encouragement of immoral Acts amongſt you, be equally beneficial to him with other Men? Eſpecially when the Gentlemen in the Country, were ſo far from offering their Service in the Expedition, that ſome of the moſt Eminent amongſt them, have abſolutely refuſed the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice; and they have been told, the Governours propoſal to the Council, about his going to the <hi>Eaſtward,</hi> met with no Oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, leſt ſome of the Military Men there, ſhould have been bound in Honour to have taken that Imployment upon them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</p>
            <p n="23">23. That ſome of the <hi>Engliſh Plantations</hi> in the <hi>Weſt-Indies,</hi> which were Contiguous to the <hi>French,</hi> ſhould be Alarm'd, is no wonder, for they were ever Jealous of their Neighbour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, and alwaies ſtood upon their Guard; but that you ſhould be afraid of being delivered up to the <hi>French,</hi> when there is neither War betwixt the two <hi>Crowns,</hi> nor any <hi>French<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men</hi>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:105757:19"/>that we can yet here of, to receive you, is one of the moſt unac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countable things in the World. From what parts muſt they come? From <hi>Canada</hi> you know they can not; they want both Men and Ships, and have reaſon enough to look to themſelves; <hi>France</hi> have their Hands full at home; and 'tis well known they cannot ſpare any from the <hi>Weſt-In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies;</hi> they made their outmoſt Effort againſt <hi>Eſtalia;</hi> and by the beſt In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligence I can get, in that Service or War, there was not one <hi>Frigat; Muſt they then drop out of the Clouds, or do you expect a Fleet from</hi> Utopia? Certainly, this muſt needs convince any conſidering Man, that theſe poor People have been extremely abus'd, and they muſt be Stupid and Senſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, who think that Sir <hi>Edmond Andros,</hi> and Ten or Twelve Men more; (for that is all the Number ſaid to be concerned in this wonderful Plot;) Could they be guilty of ſo horrid a Wickedneſs and Impiety? Were able to deliver ſo many Thouſand Men, well appointed, into the Hands of a few <hi>French-men,</hi> who <hi>from God knows whence,</hi> were to come, <hi>The Lord knows when.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="24">24. That it was either their Duty to God, or that they had the Nobility, Gentry, and Commons of <hi>England,</hi> for their Preſedent, I cannot by any means allow; and I am amaz'd to ſee <hi>Chriſtians</hi> call that a <hi>Duty,</hi> which God has ſo remarkably ſhewed his Diſpleaſure againſt, in all Countries, and Ages; Is not <hi>Rebellion, as the Sin of Witchcraft?</hi> Numb. 11.12.16. Who was it that ſent <hi>the Leproſie amongſt the Children of</hi> Iſrael, <hi>for their mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mering?</hi> Pſal. 78. Or, how came <hi>the ſudden Fire, with which they were burnt up?</hi> How many <hi>Thouſands periſhed by the Peſtilence?</hi> Or, were they a few that were <hi>ſtung to Death by the Fiery Serpents?</hi> Do we not read, that <hi>the Earth opened, and ſwallowed up ſome of their Captains, with their Wives and Children quick?</hi> which horrible Deſtruction fell upon the Children of <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael,</hi> for their <hi>murmering</hi> againſt <hi>Moſes,</hi> whom God had appointed their head, and chief Majeſtrate; What ſhall I ſay of <hi>Abſalom?</hi> What of a <hi>Achitophel?</hi> Or what of <hi>Sheba?</hi> Holy Writ is ſo full of Examples, of the like Nature, that no Body can eſteem that a Duty, which is ſo often teſtified againſt: And as it is far from being their Duty to God, ſo there is no Parellel be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Proceedings of the <hi>Lords Spiritual and Temporal in</hi> England, and theirs here; for the Deſign of Eſtabliſhing Popery and Arbitrary Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, in this Colony, is altogether Ridiculous and Incredible; for, who was to have effected it? Could thoſe few of <hi>the Church of</hi> England, that with the hazard of their Lives and Fortunes, ſo lately oppoſed it in <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope;</hi> and that in all Ages have been the only Bulwork againſt it? Or were the <hi>Presbyterians, Independants,</hi> or <hi>Anabaptiſts,</hi> to have brought this about?
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:105757:19"/>It muſt have been one of thoſe, for I dare be bold to ſay, there are not Two Roman Catholicks betwixt this and <hi>New York.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have ſufficiently demonſtrated, in the third Article, the little Right we have to any other Government in the Plantations; and that we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not juſtly call that Arbitrary, which by the Law we are obliged to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to: So that betwixt their Condition and ours, there can be no Parity.</p>
            <p>As their Reaſons and yours were different, ſo are the Meaſures which have been taken; for his late Highneſs <hi>the Prince of Orange,</hi> having well-weighed and conſidered the tottering Condition of the <hi>Proteſtant Religion</hi> all over <hi>Europe,</hi> thought it was high time for him to take up Arms, as well for his own Preſervation, as that of his Neighbours and Allies. We do not find, that notwithſtanding the Danger that hung over their heads, the People of <hi>England</hi> took up Arms to right them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; but inſtead thereof, they became humble Suppliants to his <hi>High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> for his Favour and Protection, which he was pleaſed to grant them: Neither do we find, that the Lords Spiritual and Temporal, aſſumed any Authority, for which they had no colour of Law: As they are <hi>Peers,</hi> they are inveſted with the higheſt Authority, and are the grand Conſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vators of the Peace of the Nation; they never left their Duty and Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legiance to his late MAJESTY, until he firſt left the Kingdom; and all Things were tranſacted in his Name, and by his Authority, until the very minute <hi>the Prince</hi> was proclaimed; who came not by force to Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer and Subject the Nation to a foreign Power, nor to Subvert and Deſtroy the lawful Government, but to Maintain and Support the ſame, in a peaceable manner, by a <hi>Free Parliament:</hi> The <hi>Prince,</hi> nor <hi>Peers,</hi> never abrogated nor altered any of the lawful Powers of the Nation, but ſtrengthned and confirmed all that were capable of beating Office, by which there was always a due Adminiſtration of Juſtice. <hi>The Sword</hi> was never ſaid to <hi>Rule</hi> and <hi>Sway;</hi> and by conſequence that Confuſion and Diſorder avoided, which their Illegal and <hi>Arbitrary Proceedings</hi> have precipitated us into.</p>
            <p>As to the fanciful Stories of <hi>Macquas, Subterranean Vaults, Fire-Works, French Frigats, poiſoning the Soldiers to the Eaſtward,</hi> &amp;c. they are ſo <hi>ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parently falſe,</hi> and <hi>ſtrangely ridiculous,</hi> that by this time, no Man in his Wits can believe them; and I need no Argument to confute the Credit of thoſe monſtrous Follies, ſince Time and Experience have ſufficiently demonſtrated them to be meer <hi>Lyes and Inventions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now I hope all ſober thinking Men are convinced, That the before-alledged Reaſons, are in themſelves either abſolutely falſe, or of little mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment;
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:105757:20"/>and conſequently <hi>no ſufficient ground for taking up Arms;</hi> all that remains on this head therefore, will be to ſhew,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> That if all the Reaſons had been tiue, yet it could not juſtifie their Proceedings.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> If their Condition had been as bad, and their Grievances really as great, as they were made believe, thoſe Meaſures could never mend the one, nor redreſs the other.</p>
            <p>The moſt excellent <hi>Grotius</hi> hath ſo learnedly wrote upon the firſt of thoſe, that I ſhall preſume to uſe no other Argument than his own up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that head, which you may read in 4. <hi>Cap. Lib.</hi> 1. <hi>De jure Belli &amp; Pacis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Theſe Meaſures could never better their Condition, nor re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſs their Grievances, unleſs they are ſo vain to imagine themſelves capable of waging War with the <hi>Crown of England,</hi> and all its Allies. Is the King ſo inconſiderable a Prince, that he ſhould be forced? Or can they think that the noiſe of their <hi>Thouſands and Ten Thouſands,</hi> will frighten him into a Compliance? Without doubt if they do, they will too too late find themſelves miſtaken? and a woful Experience will quickly teach them, that the ſole want of <hi>their Majeſties Protection,</hi> will, in a very ſhort time, reduce them to the moſt miſerable and deplorable Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition in the World.</p>
            <p>But, perhaps, they may fancy, that this Action of theirs, hath ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly obliged their Majeſties, and that all things now are become juſtly due to the Merits of their Services: 'Twill do very well if it be ſo underſtood; but I cannot ſee the leaſt probability of ſuch a Conſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, for they have ſufficiently manifeſted in their <hi>Declaration;</hi> that <hi>Self-Intereſt,</hi> fondneſs of their former popular Government, and averſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the Government eſtabliſh'd from <hi>England,</hi> was the firſt and princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal Motive to their Undertakings; and their Progreſs doth plainly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrate, that they have only made uſe of <hi>their Majeſties Names,</hi> the better to effect their own Deſigns, whilſt every thing that hath any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation to them lies <hi>neglected and unregarded,</hi> without any <hi>Recognition</hi> of their Authority over thoſe Dominions, or the leaſt acknowledgment of their ſubmiſſion to ſuch Orders as ſhould come from them, ſaving what particularly related to <hi>ſome few ill Men,</hi> (as they call them,) whom they they have impriſoned and detained, without any Law or Reaſon: So that they have raſhly and imprudently adventured their <hi>ALL</hi> upon a Chance, (not an equal one,) Whether it will be well or ill taken: If well, they can expect nothing more, than what they would have had by
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:105757:20"/>fitting ſtill and quiet, unleſs it be a vaſt charge, trouble, and expence: which they have inevitably brought upon themſelves: If ill, What will be the event?</p>
            <p>In the firſt place, This Country, which hath ſo much valued it ſelf, for the <hi>true Profeſſion and pure Exerciſe of the Proteſtant Religion,</hi> will be termed a Land full of <hi>Hypocriſie, Rebellion, Irriligion, and what not?</hi> and they themſelves a degenerate wicked People.</p>
            <p>Secondly, In all their Pamphlets and Diſcourſes, they have ſo magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied their Action, and boaſted of the vaſt Numbers they can bring into the Field, that it muſt be of great import to the Crown of <hi>England</hi> to <hi>curb</hi> them, &amp; in time to reduce them to their former Obedience; and no body will imagine it conſiſtant with the <hi>Intereſt</hi> of the <hi>Crown</hi> any more to truſt <hi>Government,</hi> in the hands of a People ſo ready and ſo able, upon all Occaſions, to Revolt and ſet up for themſelves; and the ſtronger they are, the more need there will be to keep them under.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, And laſtly, They will really endure and undergo all thoſe Miſeries and Calamities which they fancied to themſelves under the late Government, and become the Scorn and By-word of all their Neighbours.</p>
            <p>What then remains, but that they ſhould endeavour to ſettle themſelves in ſuch a poſture, as may at leaſt mitigate, if not wholly prevent the before-mentioned Inconveniencies? If their Charter be reſtored, it can neither juſtifie their paſt Actions, nor maintain their former Laws or Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of Government; but render them liable to be queſtioned and <hi>Quo Warranto'd</hi> for their Malefeſance, whenſoever the Supreme Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity ſhall think it meet. There is nothing therefore that can be ſafe or ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e for them, and of greater Service and Benefit, than that they put themſelves in a ſubmiſſive and humble poſture, ſit and ready to receive their Majeſties Commands; and not value themſelves too much upon their own Merits, leſt they become unworthy of their Majeſties Grace and Favour; without which, (think what you will,) they can never be ſafe and ſecure from the Severity of the Laws, which they have indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſputably violated, in Matters of the higheſt Nature and Conſequence imaginable.</p>
            <p>I hope every good Man will ſeriouſly conſider the foregoing Diſcourſe, and ſuffer himſelf to be guided by the Dictates of Reaſon, and not of Humor and Prejudice; and then I am well aſſured, it will be evident enough that they have miſtaken their Meaſures, and that a due ſence
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:105757:21"/>thereof, and a timely receſs, will more advantage them, than an obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate and wilful perſeverance; and that nothing but ſuch a Remedy can reſtore their almoſt-periſhing and undone Country, to a laſting Peace and happy Settlement; for which, ſhall ever be the hearty Prayers of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your humble Servant,</hi> J. Palmer.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <head>POSTSCRIPT.</head>
            <p>I Was principall induced to direct the precedent Diſcourſe to you, Gentlemen, for two Reaſons: Firſt, Becauſe I am well aſſured, you have had a great ſhare in the late Revolution; and, ſecondly, Becauſe I would be rightly under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, which I am ſure I can never fail of, by Perſons of your Learning and Worth; and I hope you will be ſo kind to me, and ſo juſt to your Country, to let me know, in the moſt publick manner you can, wherein I have <hi>miſtaken</hi> the Matter, either in point of Fact or Judgment: But if I have been ſo for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunate to convince you, that wrong Meaſures have been taken, and that the People had no Reaſon for what they have done, nor no Bottom for what they are yet doing, let me tell you, 'tis your Duty not only to admoniſh them, but to reduce them to ſuch a temper as becomes pious Men and good Chriſtians, for which you will have the Praiſe, and God the Glory.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>From the</hi> Caſtle <hi>the Twentieth Day of</hi> 
                  <date>June, <hi>1689.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:105757:21"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
